Guide to the Conrad Woelfel Papers TAM.796
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Conrad Woelfel Papers
1924-2008
1924-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Woelfel, Conrad
Alperin-Hochman, Marlene
TAM.796
2.48 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 flat oversized box, and 1 folder in a shared small flat box
Conrad Woelfel (1902-1989) was a German American labor leader and fraternal organizer based in Detroit and New York City. Woelfel was born in Nuremberg, Germany and emigrated to the United States in 1923. He held various labor-related positions during his life: President of Engravers Lodge 2136; an Executive Board member of District 15, Machinists Union; and for 20 years, an organizer and Secretary-Treasurer of the International Metal Engravers Union. Woelfel was also deeply engaged in the German American community, co-founding the German-American Congress for Democracy (an organization for which he served as National Secretary). He held the position of President of the Workmen's Benefit Fund for 20 years, until his retirement in 1976. The Conrad Woelfel Papers (dated 1924-2008) includes scrapbooks, correspondence, newspaper articles, and photographs documenting Woelfel's labor union organizing in New York City from the 1930s through the 1970s. The collection also contains a small amount of materials documenting the Recreation Farm Society collected by Woelfel's daughter Helen Krump. Materials in the collection show the ways in which German immigrants navigated concepts of American patriotism during World War II, and how they built solidarity, community, and support for one another.
Scope and Contents
The Conrad Woelfel Papers (dated 1924-2008) include scrapbooks, correspondence, newspaper articles, and photographs documenting Woelfel's labor union organizing in New York City from the 1930s through the 1970s, particularly his tenure as President of the Workman's Benefit Fund; and his engagement with the German American community, with an emphasis on his involvement with the German-American Congress for Democracy. The collection documents 20th century labor organizing, particularly in the greater New York City area and with an emphasis on the experiences of German and Jewish immigrants. The collection also shows the ways in which German immigrants navigated concepts of American patriotism during World War II, and how they built solidarity, community, and support for one another. Also included is a small amount of personal materials, such as family photographs, personal correspondence, a page from Woelfel's German passport, Woelfel's writing, and German newspapers. The collection also contains a small amount of materials documenting the Recreation Farm Society, which was connected to the Workman's Benefit Fund through the Women's Auxiliary. These materials, which include clippings, correspondence, and photographs, were collected by Woelfel's daughter Helen Krump.
Arrangement
Generally, this collection has been arranged chronologically, with personal materials first.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Marlene Hochman, President of the Toy Museum of New York, and Barbara Vivien, Board Member, in the memory of Helen Krump, Conrad Woelfel's daughter, in October 2020. The accession number associated with this gift is 2020.037.
Biographical Note
Conrad Woelfel (1902-1989) was a German American labor leader and fraternal organizer based in Detroit and New York City. Woelfel was born in Nuremberg, Germany and emigrated to the United States in 1923. He held various labor-related positions during his life: President of Engravers Lodge 2136; an Executive Board member of District 15, Machinists Union; and for 20 years, an organizer and Secretary-Treasurer of the International Metal Engravers Union. Woelfel was also deeply engaged in the German American community, co-founding the German-American Congress for Democracy (an organization for which he served as National Secretary). He held the position of President of the Workmen's Benefit Fund for 20 years, until his retirement in 1976. The Recreation Farm Society was part of the Women's Auxiliary of the Workmen's Benefit Fund; both Woelfel's wife, Betty, and daughter, Helen, were involved; Helen served as president in the late 1970s.
German Americans -- Ethnic identity; World War, 1939-1945.; Labor unions -- New York (N.Y.); Scrapbooks.; Fraternal organizations; Labor leaders -- New York (N.Y.); Alperin-Hochman, Marlene; Workmen's Benefit Fund of the United States of America
- Personal, 1924-1990
  - German Newspapers, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs, 1929-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, Correspondence, Biographies, and German Passport, 1949-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writings, 1953-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- International Medal Engravers Union, 1933-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- German-American Congress for Democracy, 1941-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Office of Labor Affairs, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Workmen's Benefit Fund, 1956-1990
  - Speeches, Press Releases, and Clippings, 1956-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1956-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8, Box Shared Tamiment 164, Folder 25)
- Scrapbooks, 1924-1979
  - Untitled Scrapbook, 1924-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Days of Yore", 1941-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - "We Promise to Uphold the Dignity of Man", 1941-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
- Recreation Farm Society, circa early 1950s-2008
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Meeting Minutes, 1966-2008 (Box 2, Folder 1, Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, circa early 1950s-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2-6)